בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we are today נזיר דף ד, Nazir Daf
Dalet, and we pick up right at the top,
and let's just take it from אלא כי הא, Ella k'ha, the
top line. We'll reread the last line that we read yesterday. So
the issue here is that the גמרא, Gemara, the משנה Mishnah said
that if somebody becomes, wants to be a נזיר nazir just from
one aspect of what a נזיר nazir involves, only from let's say
the grapes, or only from shaving, or only from טומאה, tumah, it's
a whole package. It's all or
nothing. The גמרא Gemara quotes the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that also agrees it's a whole package, but that says that if
you didn't do everything you did nothing. Of course there's a possible
third position which is not voiced or not represented, maybe doesn't exist
it seems, that actually could allow for a partial נזירות. nezirut. That
is something that the גמרא Gemara rejects. We are going to see
in the coming משנה Mishnah that there is a something called נזיר
שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, because as we know שמשון Shimshon got טמא tamei
on a regular basis,
but other than that, there is no phenomenon of partial נזירות. nezirut.
Okay, so this is the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
the רבנן, Rabbanan, and the גמרא Gemara like it often does tries
to sort of figure out what פסוק pasuk is one, you know,
are they each getting their hint from, they're each getting their position
from, and then what does the other one do with the פסוק
pasuk that that one had used. So in that regard, the most
immediate focus of the גמרא Gemara was the פסוק pasuk that says
מיין ושכר יזיר, Miyayin veshechar yazir, which is that a, that somebody
will become a נזיר nazir from wine and intoxicating liquid. As we
said yesterday, intoxicating liquid does not mean what it normally does, which
is like, you know, intoxicating liquid, beer, or something of that nature,
mead, because the חז"ל Chazal understand that in the context of נזיר
nazir it only means when there's a mixture of wine, which is
interesting, not פשט pshat in the פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, it says from
that, so meaning even from only that if, you know, that even
if only he tried to become a נזיר nazir from something, from
a little thing, actually it would pull everything in. So then it
says, so what does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon do with that פסוק?
pasuk? That seems to be an extra פסוק. pasuk. And he's saying
that פסוק pasuk is coming to tell me that even a type
of a wine which I thought might be excluded, the נזיר nazir
is still forbidden from that wine. What wine might I have thought
is excluded? So first the גמרא Gemara says wine of קידוש kiddush
and הבדלה. havdalah. Okay, that gets rejected as we read, it was
a very strange line in the גמרא. Gemara. It said מושבע ועומד
מהר סיני. mushba ve'omed me'har sinai. Since when is wine of קידוש
kiddush and הבדלה havdalah דאורייתא? de'oraita? And most ראשונים Rishonim follow רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam who read that to say, give me a break.
It's not מושבע ועומד מהר סיני, mushba ve'omed me'har sinai, meaning he
meant it ironically or rhetorically. Okay, you don't need a פסוק pasuk
to say that you can't drink the wine of קידוש kiddush and
הבדלה. havdalah. That's obvious. A נזיר, nazir, you're not drinking the wine
of קידוש kiddush and הבדלה. havdalah. Okay, so what's the issue? אלא,
Ella, so picking up again from now the top line of ד'
עמוד א'. dalet amud aleph. אלא כי הא דאמר רבא, Ella ki
ha de'amar Rava, so what you need the פסוק pasuk to tell
me that some wine remains off, you know, is forbidden and I
might have thought that maybe it wouldn't be, כי הא דאמר רבא
ki ha de'amar Rava to tell me what רבא Rava teaches me.
שבועה אשתה, Shevuah eshteh, somebody takes a שבועה shevuah that they will
drink wine. I'm, somebody says I'm going to drink wine today. וחזר
ואמר הרי אני נזיר, Vechazar ve'amar harey ani nazir, and then you're
saying I'm a נזיר nazir today right afterwards. So I might think
that, you know, you can't, you're already forsworn to drink wine and
your נזירות nezirut can't come and override that, and maybe you have
to drink the wine. So I might think, nevertheless, אתיא נזירות חיילא
על שבועה, asya nezirut chayla al shevuah,
that no, from all wine you're forbidden, even from that wine and
you can't drink the wine and you have to deal with the
fact that you're going to violate your שבועה. shevuah. And the reason
for this is, as we've discussed, that you if you're מושבע ועומד
מהר סיני, mushba ve'omed me'har sinai, if you are obligated to do
something either because the תורה Torah obligates you or because you accepted
a שבועה, shevuah, you cannot obligate yourself to do the opposite. So
I cannot say if it's a personal obligation, I cannot say a
שבועה shevuah I'm not going to sit in a סוכה sukkah on
סוכות. Succos. I'm already obligated. Or if I say a שבועה shevuah
I'm going to drink wine, I can't a minute later say a
שבועה shevuah I'm not going to drink wine. I've already obligated myself,
that would directly countermand my preexisting obligation. However, you can take a
נדר neder because a נדר neder works indirectly. If I say all
סוכות sukkahs are forbidden to me, right? Then when it comes, I'm
not saying I'm not going to do the מצוה, mitzvah, I'm not
directly relating to my personal obligation. I'm just making the physical object
of the סוכה sukkah forbidden to me. Then when it comes time
to do my מצוה, mitzvah, נעבעך, nebach, I can't. There's no way
I can do it. It's a forbidden object. So similarly, even if
I took a שבועה shevuah to drink wine, I'm not saying I'm
not going to drink wine, I'm just saying I'm a נזיר. nazir.
Okay, and then it's just the natural consequence of that is that
now that I've defined my personal status as a נזיר, nazir, one
of the things I'm not allowed to do is drink wine but
I'm not directly countermanding my obligation. I'm relating either to the object
like the סוכה sukkah object, or in this important idea of נזיר,
nazir, I'm the object. Okay, so when a נזיר, nazir, somebody says
they're going to be a נזיר, nazir, they're not directly obligating themselves
not to drink wine, not to do this, not to do that,
etc. They are just changing their definition, they're changing their identity, they're
imparting a status upon themselves to be a נזיר nazir and then
everything else flows from that and flows from the תורה's Torah obligation
for a נזיר. nazir. Okay, so you're the object for a נזיר.
nazir. Anyway, that's why it works. So even in that case, you're
forbidden to drink the wine. All right, now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: רבנן נמי מיבעי ליה למעוטי יין מצוה ויין רשות. Rabbanan
nami mibei lei lema'utei yayin mitzvah veyayin reshus. One minute. The Rabbis
also need that פסוק pasuk to teach me that thing, that that
wine is even though it's a מצוה mitzvah obligation because you took
a שבועה, shavuah, still is forbidden on you. So they can't use
that verse to teach me that even a you tried to be
a נזיר Nazir for part, you're a נזיר Nazir for
everything. No, אם כן נימא קרא מיין, im kein nima kra mi-yayin,
if all it wanted to teach you was that even this type
of wine is forbidden to you, let it just say 'from wine'.
מאי ושכר, mai v'sheichar, why does it add intoxicating liquid? So why
does it say both? שמע מינה תרתי shma mina tarti to tell
you that even if you just try to be a נזיר Nazir
for part, even just from שכר, sheichar, you're a נזיר Nazir for
everything. So we have a little extra piece of the פסוק pasuk
that teaches me that. ורבי שמעון, v'Rabbi Shimon, היינו טעמא דכתיב שכר,
hainu ta'ama dechtiv sheichar, so what would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon explain,
why why is it teaching שכר, sheichar, what's that extra piece of
the פסוק pasuk doing? לאלופי שכר שכר למקדש l'alufei sheichar sheichar l'mikdash
to learn out to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. דכתיב יין ושכר
אל תשת אתה ובניך אתך, dechtiv yayin v'sheichar al teisht ata u-vanecha
itach, wine and intoxicating liquid you cannot drink you and your children
with you. So or your sons more
literally. ובבאכם אל אהל מועד או בגישתם אל המזבח לשרת. u-ve-vo'achem el
ohel mo'ed o b'gishtam el ha-mizbei'ach l'shareis. Okay, so anyway, that a
כהן kohein should not be drunk when he enters into the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And that, by the way, includes שכר. sheichar. Here
שכר sheichar halachically does mean שכר, sheichar, even if
so for a כהן kohein to drink wine, actually it's interesting. When
it comes to wine, there's a formal definition of how much wine,
a רביעית, revi'is, which is not a lot, which is like, you
know, a Kiddush cup, less, I mean, most of our Kiddush cups
are bigger than a רביעית, revi'is, three and a half ounces. Okay,
when it comes to שכר, sheichar, it has to be enough that
it actually gets makes them drunk. Okay, so כהן kohein is not
allowed to be have drunk wine or to be drunk when they
enters into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So, מה גבי נזיר יין
הוא דליסר ושאר משקין שרו? ma gabi Nazir yayin hu d'lissar v'sha'ar
mashkin sharu? By נזיר, Nazir, we
said, and this is what I just mentioned at the beginning, even
though it says יין ושכר, yayin v'sheichar, what we really say is
just wine and not other liquids, not other beverages. אף
גבי מקדש, af gabi Mikdash, so because יין ושכר yayin v'sheichar is
linked from נזיר Nazir to the מקדש, Mikdash, it's teaching you נמי
יין הוא דליסר ושאר משקין המשכרין שרו, nami yayin hu d'lissar v'sha'ar
mashkin hamishkarin sharu, that only wine but not other liquids that get
one drunk, even though again, that's pretty much what the word שכר
sheichar means. Okay, because we are, I mean, it's a great logic.
We're taking the simple word שכר, sheichar, which clearly means non-wine like
mead, beer, intoxicating liquid, we'll say in the context of נזיר Nazir
it can't mean that. It's got to be all about grapes. It's
got to be some type of a wine-based type of a drink.
And therefore, since it uses the same phrase by a כהן, kohein,
יין ושכר yayin v'sheichar by there also it must not mean not
really שכר, sheichar, it must really mean just something that's wine-based. Okay,
and that's what we do with this extra phrase שכר. sheichar. Okay,
ולאפוקי מדרבי יהודה ul'apukei mid'Rabbi Yehuda and to and to reject the
position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, detanya, in a ברייתא, Baraisa,
רבי יהודה אומר אכל דבילה קעילית, Rabbi Yehuda omer achal dveilah ke'ilis,
if a person eats a pressed... I can always get mixed up,
which are the figs and the dates? I think this is dates,
right? What what one of your Englishers must say, the dates? Okay,
figs. Oh, okay, got it wrong. I just I right now it's
a great time to eat figs, they're like, anyway, I just had
a whole round of them last night. Okay, anyway. So אכל, achal,
I think they're all like available a lot in the שוק, shuk,
market. Anyway, אכל דבילה קעילית, achal dveilah ke'ilis, if somebody eats this
these figs from this place קעילית, Ke'ilis, ושתה דבש וחלב, v'shasa dvash
v'chalav, or drink honey and milk. You remember the whole story there
with with what's her name and סיסרא, Sisra, יעל Yael and סיסרא.
Sisra. ונכנס למקדש חייב v'nichnas l'mikdash chayav and entered into the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, he's חייב, chayav, because all these things, even some
of them are not even drinks, some of them are food. Okay,
nevertheless, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, these are things that can
get a person drunk, okay, that can make a person like a
little bit high, let's say. And therefore, all of that is included
in שכר. sheichar. So so שכר sheichar for him includes all these
things. And the Rabbis are saying no, not other things, not שאר
דברים המשכרין. sha'ar devarim hamishkarin. Now the point here is there's a
diff you know, there's a bit of a gap between those two.
What רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does is he takes the little word
שכר, sheichar, which refers to a particular type of a beverage, and
he applies it to anything that will impart this state of, you
know, drunkenness or being high, right? And of this list here, you
know, some of these aren't even beverages. Okay, you could have reasonably
rejected רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda but still said, but if you drink
beer, you drink mead, literally שכר, sheichar, you are חייב. chayav. Okay,
and even though this גמרא Gemara sounds like it's saying a position
that even for entering the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it would have
to be wine and we wouldn't read the word שכר sheichar literally,
that's not the way we פוסקן. pasken. We do פוסקן pasken that
שכר, sheichar, you know, a person is חייב, chayav, and we even
tend to פוסקן pasken like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that even other
things המשכרין. hamishkarin. Okay, but again, the simple sense of this פסוק
pasuk is quite interesting. Since שכר sheichar can't mean it by נזיר,
Nazir, it'd have to mean wine-based, then as I... this
לימוד limud and with the whole מסכת נדרים. masechet Nedarim. Somebody came
to me and said that they were on a בית דין, beis
din, I'm trying to remember, I thought they said they were on
a בית דין beis din for מתיר נדר, matir neder, but it
was...
yeah I think they said, I think that's what it was. I'm
trying to remember if they said a בית דין beis din for
גירות geirus or בית דין beis din for מתיר נדר. matir neder.
I think it was a בית דין beis din for גירות geirus
and wanted to know because they had taken some type of a
drug because they had very serious muscle pain. And so the drug
gave them a little bit of a high, right? It was a
state. So says was that פסול pasul because not only as a
כהן kohen can't enter the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but you can't
be מורה הלכה moreh halacha if you are drunk. And if we
rule that drunk is not just defined as through some type of
a intoxicating beverage, but through eating figs, so you know maybe it's
through taking medicine. Oh, but you have to say it has to
be eating and medicine is even considered eating? Not necessarily, right? I
mean once it's things that cause that state, maybe even some type
of medication. So I think it's reasonable that that actually would be
a problem even if it came through drugs, but the הלכה halacha
is it's not you're not allowed to sit on a בית דין
beis din if you're drunk, it's you're not allowed to פוסקן pasken
a halachic שאלה. shaila. And one of the ways you know is
it says in שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch if you just say if
you're just telling somebody what's already written בספרים basforim you're just saying
yeah it's a מפורש mofurash שלחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. That's not פוסקן.
paskening. That you're allowed to do when you're drunk. So it's not
necessarily playing that role of being a דיין dayan or something, but
it was a very interesting question. Yeah.
Well, jokingly if you can remember the סימן siman in שלחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch maybe you're not really drunk.
Well, right, right. Or more points...
there's
the figs they describe there can actually be fermented. Oh, that's interesting.
And couldn't they... but they might also be talking about a sugar
high kind of thing. Uh-huh, uh-huh.
Yeah, but if you eat a straight fig it won't ferment as
a fig, right?
No, no, but you can ferment it.
Uh-huh, uh-huh, yeah.
They show animals getting drunk on them, it's actually hilarious. Really? Honestly,
yeah. So like you have a fig tree and then you have
a group of pigeons underneath it. Yeah. Completely blotted.
Really? How do figs make make... I think there's something in it.
The sugar or something. Fantastic. Oh my god. Okay. What?
It's a poacher's trick. Yeah, I know when that happens.
Oh, I see. Amazing, amazing. Okay, thank you. All right.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. איבעית אימא Iba'is eima or you
could say... yes.
Does this הלכה halacha apply to a כהן kohen before the עבודה
avoda in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Yeah, about דברים המשתכרין. devarim
hamishtakrin.
Yeah, yeah,
that's what this is about. It's about כהן. kohen. It's just then
we also apply it to being מורה הוראה. moreh hora'ah. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says this. איבעית אימא Iba'is eima and if you
want I could say that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that again what
is this extra פסוק pasuk about יין yayin coming to tell me
even a even certain wine is forbidden, what's that teaching me? רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon לית ליה lais lay איסור חל על איסור isur
chal al isur because רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon generally does not hold
of the idea of one איסור isur taking effect on top of
another. Once something has a forbidden status it doesn't get no double
jeopardy, it can't get a double forbidden status. דתניא, Detanya, we taught
in a ברייתא. braisa. רבי שמעון אומר: Rebbi Shimon omer: האוכל נבלה
ביום הכפורים פטור. Ha'ochel neveila b'Yom Kippur patur.
If somebody eats a animal carcass a נבלה neveila on יום כפור
Yom Kippur you're exempt from violating יום כפור. Yom Kippur. Because it's
אין איסור חל על איסור. ein isur chal al isur. So now
of course this is bizarre because it's one thing to say that
something cannot get a double status if it's the status of the
object. Like if something is a נבלה neveila and then I go
ahead and cook it in milk, so I go ahead and have
a McDonald's hamburger which starts off as a נבלה neveila and then
I put on some cheese on it if you could you know,
so now does it also become בשר בחלב? basar b'chalav? So you
could say that's the double status of the object itself and once
it has one status of forbidden you don't double it up with
another status of something forbidden. So if I were to eat that
I would only transgress נבלה, neveila, not בשר בחלב. basar b'chalav. That's
a normal thing I mean that makes sense. But the funny thing
is that the whole source of רבי שמעון's Rebbi Shimon's position is
by יום כפור. Yom Kippur. And יום כפור Yom Kippur the prohibition
is not on the object, it's on me, right? So what if
the object is forbidden? I am still prohibited from violating my sense
of עינוי inuy and I violated it. Why does that status of
the object mean I don't violate יום כפור? Yom Kippur? So it's
very hard to understand that application of רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon which
is his prime application.
But you could obviously say he should be עובר oiver on the
אכילה achila and forget the נבלה.
neveila. No, but he doesn't. He says you're not you're not עובר
over on יום כפור. Yom Kippur. You would argue... Yeah, yeah, so
he doesn't. So anyway, so that's the whole discussion of רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon איסור חל על איסור. isur chal al isur. We're only
bringing it in to tell me that that doesn't apply by a
נזיר. nazir. If for example I took a שבועה, shevua, the opposite
of what we said before. Not a שבועה shevua I will drink
wine, I took a שבועה shevua I won't drink wine. And now
I go ahead and I say I'm a נזיר. nazir. And then
I drink wine. So here רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say again
from the פסוק pasuk מיין ושכר יזיר miyayin v'sheichar yazir that I'm
also even in that case I'm Forbidden on the wine, not just
because of my שבועה, shvua, but also because of my נזירות. nezirot.
Okay, and that would be a case where we would say איסור
חל על איסור issur chal al issur even though normally he does
not. Yeah, חייב chayav twice. Even according to Rabbi Shimon. That's again
what we're saying, what he does with the פסוק pasuk מיין ושכר
יזיר. miyayin v'sheichar yazir. One thing he did is to say it
applies even if you took a שבועה shvua not to do it,
and here we're saying it applies even if you took a שבועה
shvua to do it. Either way, the שבועה shvua still applies. And
partly because as I said, נזיר nazir is about changing my status,
not about creating obligations. Yes.
In the case of the eating נבילה neveila on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, those two prohibitions came into effect at the same time.
No, the animal- oh, if it died on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So the גמרא Gemara actually says that Rabbi Shimon would agree if
it died on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but if it died- we're
talking about that it died before יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So it
was already אסור assur to me as a נבילה neveila before יום
כיפור Yom Kippur came around. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. ורבנן
נמי הכתיב מכל אשר יעשה מגפן היין. Ul'rabanan nami hachtiv michol asher
ye'aseh migefen hayayin. Okay, but now the Rabbis, what do they do
with Rabbi Shimon's פסוק pasuk that says if you try to do
part you get off? What's Rabbi Shimon's פסוק? pasuk? It says from
everything that's made of wine and of, you know, grapes and wine.
And everything for Rabbi Shimon means you have to do everything and
if you only tried to do part you did nothing. So he
emphasizes the מכל. michol. You have to fundamentally accept נזירות nezirot from
everything. Okay, if you try to do part, nothing happens. So אמרי
ליה רבנן, Amri leh rabanan, here's what they do with that פסוק.
pasuk. התם לימד על איסור נזיר שמצטרפין זה עם זה. Hatam limed
al issur nazir shemitztarfin zeh im zeh.
מכל אשר יעשה Michol asher ye'aseh means you can combine them. Any
types of things that come from wine you're forbidden, which means if
I take a little bit of grape skin and a little bit
of wine- well, actually wine would be a drink, so that might
not combine. But let's say a little bit of grape skin and
a little bit of seeds and, you know, some raisins and different
types of things and it all combined to be a כזית kezayit
and I ate it, I would violate because it doesn't have to
be just one type of food. It's מכל אשר יעשה michol asher
ye'aseh from all the different types of things they all combine. Okay,
now מצטרף. mitztaref. Now we'll talk later about whether liquids combine with
solids and so on, but anyway that's what you get from it,
not though that you have to make yourself a נזיר nazir from
all or else you did nothing. So- so now
Rabbi Shimon, now why- what would Rabbi Shimon say? Where does he
know- where does he get that idea from? לית ליה צירוף. Leit
leh tziruf. He doesn't hold of this whole idea of combining. He-
or he doesn't need it. Why does he not need it? דתניא,
Detanya, we joined a ברייתא, braita, Rabbi Shimon אומר, omer, כל שהוא
למלקות. kol shehu l'malkot. It's a general position in ש"ס, Shas, he
basically teaches it in מסכת מכות Masechet Makot that all of the
time we say there's a minimum amount you need to transgress, a
כזית, kezayit, he says no, no, no. You biblically transgressed when you
did even the smallest amount and you'll even- it's even enough to
be punished, you'll even get lashes if appropriate. So then is there
an idea of שיעור shiur for him? Yes. When does a שיעור
shiur apply? לא אמרו כזית אלא לעניין קרבן. Lo amru kezayit ela
l'inyan korban. The idea of an olive size is only a minimum
amount to bring a קרבן. korban. Fascinating idea, right? A small- if
you do it willfully, right, maybe it's the מזיד meizid element of
it that makes it more severe, than even the smallest amount you've
violated and you get the punishment. If you did it unintentionally and
it's a question of having to bring a קרבן, korban, then it's
only a problem once it reaches a certain degree, then there's a
minimum amount. That's Rabbi Shimon's position. So by a נזיר nazir for
lashes, he doesn't need the idea of צירוף. tziruf. Even the tiniest
amount of wine, the tiniest amount of grapes you've transgressed, there's no
idea of lashes you get lashes. There's no idea of a minimum
you get lashes. In terms of a קרבן, korban, you don't bring
a קרבן korban for violating נזירות. nezirot. You bring a קרבן korban
either for ending נזירות nezirot or for becoming טמא. tamei. Okay, so
for him there's no implication here, no place where you need this
idea of מצטרף. mitztaref. You don't need it to get lashes, that
you get for a tiny amount. You don't need it to bring
a קרבן korban because you don't get a קרבן korban for eating,
you know, grapes and wine. You bring a קרבן korban for ending
or for becoming טמא. tamei. Yes.
So a woman who's pregnant on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and needs
to eat פחות פחות מכשיעור pachot pachot mich'shiur according to Rabbi Shimon,
she wouldn't have to eat like a little bit at a
time.
That's an interesting question. Maybe, maybe not. Again, maybe it's the מזיד
meizid element that gives it more weight. So when you're- when you
have a license to eat, then he might concede that there's a
difference between a smaller amount and a larger amount. I don't know,
it's a fascinating question. I'll have to think about it. Yeah.
Is it only Rabbi Shimon who holds that it's a violation of
נזירות nezirot on less than a כזית? kezayit?
Yes. I mean- well, look, there's a general principle that חצי שיעור
chatzi shiur is an איסור, issur, you know, we rule like Rabbi
Yochanan and the debate Rabbi Yochanan Resh Lakish. We say חצי שיעור
chatzi shiur is an איסור דאורייתא, issur d'Oraita, but it's not the
same degree of violation. Okay, so yes, by all things that you're
forbidden to eat, there's a degree of violation even if you eat
less than the minimum amount, but it's not- it's not Rabbi Shimon's
point. Rabbi Shimon's point is it's a full violation if you eat
the minimum- even there is no minimum amount. Okay, so let's take
a look. So that was fascinating. Again, in one of these classic
cases where the גמרא Gemara says what do you do with this
פסוק? pasuk? Well, what does he do with that פסוק? pasuk? What
does he do with that פסוק? pasuk? It gave us an opportunity
to have a nice little survey of some aspects of a נזיר
nazir which we're going to get to as we
continue. Right? יין מצוה ויין הרשות Yayin mitzvah v'yayin harashut and, you
know, what is שכר? sheichar? or nothing, there is one type of
נזירות nezirut *nezirut* that is not, that is partial. And that's נזירות
שמשון neziros Shimshon *Nezirut Shimshon*. If somebody says, הריני כשמשון *Hareini k'Shimshon*,
behold I will be like שמשון Shimshon *Shimshon*, or well let's assume
it means or, we'll see in a minute, כבן מנוח *k'ben Manoach*,
מנוח *Manoach*'s son, son, מנוח *Manoach*'s son. כבעל דלילה
*k'ba'al Delilah*, like דלילה *Delilah*'s husband. כמי שעקר דלתות עזה *k'mi she'akar
daltot Azza*, excuse me, it says somebody the person who tore down
the doors in עזה *Azza*, you know where that was he was
bound there by the chains. כמי שנקרו פלשתים את עיניו *k'mi shenakru
Pelishtim et einav*, I'll be like the one who the Philistines poked
out his eyes. So הרי זה נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon, *harei zeh
nazir Shimshon*. So we got the point. So all those cases you're
referring to שמשון Shimshon *Shimshon* and right, you are referring to שמשון
Shimshon *Shimshon* and you have this the bigger חידוש *chiddush* is not
just what words do it but there is this institution called נזיר
שמשון Nazir Shimshon *Nazir Shimshon* which we will see in the next
משנה Mishna *mishna* is a type of is something where you do
not violate or violate to the same degree by becoming טמא tamei,
*tamei* because שמשון Shimshon *Shimshon* became טמא tamei, *tamei* quite a bit.
Okay, טמא למת tamei lameit, *tamei l'met*, right, to dead people. So
all right, killed lot of people. Okay, so let's see what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. למה לי למתני כל הלין *Lamo li l'misni
kol hallin*? Why do you have to say all of these examples?
So צריכא *tzericha*, you need to. אי אמר הריני כשמשון *Iye amar
Hareini k'Shimshon*, if he just said behold I'm like שמשון Shimshon. *Shimshon*,
הוה אמינא שמשון Shimshon אחרינא *hava amina Shimshon achrina*, I don't know
there are a lot of שמשונים *Shimshons* around. Who knows which שמשון
Shimshon *Shimshon* you're talking about? Okay, קא משמע לן כבן מנוח *kamashma
lan k'ben Manoach*. Okay, so therefore it says כבן מנוח *k'ben Manoach*.
Now, ואי תנא כבן מנוח *v'ee tana k'ben Manoach*, if it just
said כבן מנוח *k'ben Manoach*, הוה אמינא איכא דמסקרי *hava amina ika
d'miskari*, there are other people that are called בן מנוח *ben Manoach*,
okay, so how do
I know who you're talking about? קא משמע לן כבעל דלילה *kamashma
lan k'ba'al Delilah*, so therefore it says like the husband of דלילה
*Delilah*. Now, the interesting thing is, וכמי שנקרו פלשתים את עיניו *u'k'mi
shenakru Pelishtim et einav*, and the one who the Philistines poked out
his eyes. Now the thing about this is though, it sounds like
that you it's not enough to say הריני כשמשון *Hareini k'Shimshon*. It
sounds like what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is saying is if you
say הריני כשמשון *Hareini k'Shimshon* you might mean somebody else and you
have to clarify it by saying בן מנוח *ben Manoach* and if
you say בן מנוח *ben Manoach* you might mean somebody else and
then you'd have to clarify that until you finally got to בעל
דלילה *ba'al Delilah*, it's not presumably בעל דלילה *ba'al Delilah*, it's דלילה
*Delilah* in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, right? בעל דלילה *ba'al Delilah*, it's
presumably דלילה *Delilah*, that's already clear enough, I don't know, until we
start, I mean now now there are kids called נמרוד *Nimrod* so
maybe we'll have I don't know if anybody's called דלילה *Delilah* these
days. Anyway, so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says that's actually true, which is
fascinating, that the read of the משנה Mishna *mishna* is not A
or B or C, it's you have to say כשמשון כבן מנוח
כבעל דלילה *k'Shimshon k'ben Manoach k'ba'al Delilah* until we say that it
means נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon? *Nazir Shimshon*. However, תוספות *Tosafot* says the
second part of the משנה mishna *mishna*, כמי שעקר דלתות עזה *k'mi
she'akar daltot Azza*, כמי שנקרו פלשתים את עיניו *k'mi shenakru Pelishtim et
einav*, he says that stands by itself. That's pretty explicit what you
mean. But again, it's not פשט pshat *p'shat* in the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* doesn't say it explicitly and it's certainly not פשט *p'shat* of
a משנה mishna *mishna*. The משנה mishna *mishna* seems pretty clear that
any one of these phrases suffices.
It's meant to say you have to say all of these phrases,
right? הריני כשמשון בן מנוח בעל דלילה *Hareini k'Shimshon ben Manoach ba'al
Delilah*.
Uh huh. Oh one more time what are you saying?
If it does mean to say you have to say all of
these phrases, you have to say הריני כשמשון *Hareini k'Shimshon*, בן מנוח
*ben Manoach*, בעל דלילה *ba'al Delilah*.
Yeah, it's a very good point. Yeah, yeah, it's a very good
point.
But then why does the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* go on to the
others?
Yeah, I don't know. Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does say קא
משמע לן כבעל דלילה וכמי שנקרו פלשתים את עיניו *kamashma lan k'ba'al
Delilah u'k'mi shenakru Pelishtim et einav* so maybe it means בעל דלילה
*ba'al Delilah* isn't enough for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. I don't
know. Look, what it is consistent with is what we saw yesterday,
last two days according to שמואל *Shmuel*. The משנה mishna *mishna* sounds
like a lot of phrases work, right? הריני כזה *Hareini k'zeh*, אהא
נאה *ehei na'eh* and so on, and שמואל *Shmuel* says that's not
clear enough. You need something that makes it much more clear what
you mean, you need the נזיר Nazir *nazir* walking in front of
you, you need to be holding on to your hair. So this
is in consistent with that idea that the משנה mishna *mishna* is
prepared to allow vaguer, I mean this isn't even so vague, but
okay, vaguer terms to work and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* needs it
to be more explicit. So we're it's again very consistent with what
we've seen in the last two days. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
takes these terms which are like or, or, or in the משנה
mishna *mishna*, any one of them, and as דב *Dov* points out
correctly, the כ *chaf* makes it even clearer and says that you
need to do at least the first few terms have they require
one another. Okay, let's take a look now at the next משנה
mishna *mishna* where we get to this idea of what נזירות שמשון
neziros Shimshon *Nezirut Shimshon* is. מה בין נזיר עולם לנזיר שמשון mah
bein Nazir Olam leNazir Shimshon? *Mah bein nazir olam l'nazir Shimshon*? What
is the difference between a somebody who is a נזיר עולם Nazir
Olam *nazir olam* for life and נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon *Nazir Shimshon*?
Now נזיר עולם Nazir Olam *nazir olam* is also a different institution
because you know, it doesn't just mean you haven't gotten around to
bringing your קרבן korban. *korban*. You could be a your נזירות nezirut.
*nezirut* doesn't end until you bring a קרבן korban. *korban* and I
assume people know
that
רב קוק *Rav Kook* had a student called the נזיר Nazir *Nazir*
who actually accepted נזירות nezirut *nezirut* and was a נזיר Nazir. *nazir*
for his whole life as there's no בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* and
he never brought a קרבן korban *korban*. Now I don't know Now
I don't know how he accepted his נזירות nezirut *nezirus*, but it's
possible he was not a נזיר עולם Nazir Olam *nazir olam* even
though he actually was a נזיר Nazir? *nazir* for his whole life,
but that just means he didn't end his נזירות nezirut. *nezirus*. נזיר
עולם Nazir Olam? *nazir olam* is a type of נזירות nezirut? *nezirus*
where you say I'm accepting upon myself to be a נזיר Nazir
*nazir* forever. Okay, which also was like שמשון Shimshon. *Shimshon*. שמשון Shimshon
*Shimshon* did not have a thirty day נזירות nezirut. *nezirus*. Okay, so
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is there's this other institution
also called נזיר עולם Nazir Olam. *nazir olam*, which by definition your
נזירות nezirut *nezirus* does not end. Okay, yes.
I read an article about the נזיר Nazir. *Nazir*, it was in
Tablet. Oh really?
Okay, good to know.
And did he, did he renew his נזירות nezirut *nezirus* every?
You don't have to renew it. It doesn't end until you bring
a קרבן korban *korban*. After thirty days you are, it's, you're allowed
to terminate it by bringing a קרבן korban, *korban*. Okay, but if
you don't it just keeps on going. But that's not a נזיר
עולם Nazir Olam *nazir olam*. That's somebody who just is choosing not
to end it. A נזיר עולם nazir olam *nazir olam* is by
definition I'm a נזיר Nazir *nazir* for life, which is also what
שמשון Shimshon *Shimshon* was, but that's a separate idea. Okay. Can
that be revoked? That, whether you have שאילה *she'eila* by נזירות nezirus,
*nezirus*, whether you can go to a חכם *chacham* to מתיר *matir*
the נדר neder *neder* and retroactively undo it is a discussion that
we're going to have. And it's actually a difference. You know, since
you asked the question, let's read just one line in the תוספות
*Tosfos*, five lines down. מה בין נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon. לנזיר עולם
Olam *Ma bein nazir Shimshon lenazir olam*? תוספות *Tosfos* says ואם תאמר
שאילה איכא בינייהו *ve'im tomar she'eila ika beinayhu*. How about getting it
revoked, going to a חכם *chacham* and undoing it? דנזיר שמשון Shimshon,
ליתא בשאילה *denazir Shimshon leisa beshe'eila*, נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon *nazir Shimshon*
we're going to learn later, cannot be undone. Okay, ונזיר עולם Olam
איתא בשאילה *venazir olam isa beshe'eila*, נזיר Nazir. עולם *nazir olam* can
be. So at least there's one out even by נזיר Nazir. עולם
*nazir olam*. So then תוספות *Tosfos* says yeah, well he didn't want
to give differences of how you can get out of it. We
wanted to give differences of when you're actually a, when you are
a נזיר Nazir, *nazir*, what are differences in terms of, in terms
of, you know, practicing as a נזיר Nazir *nazir*. Okay, but yes,
נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon. *nazir Shimshon* cannot be revoked, other נזירויות *neziruses*
can. But let's get back to the משנה *mishna*. So מה בין
נזיר Nazir. עולם לנזיר שמשון Shimshon *ma bein nazir olam lenazir Shimshon*?
What is the difference between a permanent נזירות nezirut? *nezirus* and נזירות
nezirut שמשון Shimshon's *nezirus Shimshon*, which also is permanent? So נזיר Nazir,
עולם הכביד שערו מיקל בתער ומביא שלש בהמות *nazir olam hichbid se'aro
meikel beta'ar umevi shalosh behemot*. So somebody who is a נזיר nazir
עולם *nazir olam*, so you know, he's going to get start having
very, very long hair. So we actually learn out, and we'll see
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to learn out from אבשלום *Avshalom*,
that this is actually that there's a, the תורה *Torah* allows such
a person to cut his hair, you know, periodically cut his hair
to cut down on how heavy and, you know, his hair has
become. Okay, now that's amazing because the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*, you would
think you're a נזיר nazir *nazir*, you're doing it, you're violating a
biblical prohibition. Okay, but the חז"ל *Chazal* learn out, it's, this is
like just fascinating for a moment to appreciate it, that you have
the biblical institution of נזיר nazir. *nazir*, you have actually two things
in נ"ך *Nach* later of actual cases, שמשון Shimshon. *Shimshon* and אבשלום
*Avshalom*, and actually from them we are going to say this teaches
us that there actually are variants to this נזירות nezirut, *nezirut* that
are not in the תורה *Torah*, that have actually have more leniencies.
You can be a נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon, *nazir Shimshon* and become
טמא tamei. למת *tamei lemet*. You can be a נזיר nazir, עולם
*nazir olam* and be allowed to cut your hair
periodically. Both of which seem to directly violate biblical prohibitions. Nevertheless, we're
learning out from these actual cases in נ"ך *Nach* that these different
institutions of נזירות nezirut *nezirut* exist. Okay. So נזיר nazir, עולם הכביד
שערו מיקל בתער *nazir olam hichbid se'aro meikel beta'ar*. You do have
an, you are able to cut your hair if it gets too
heavy. You can use a razor. ומביא שלש בהמות *umevi shalosh behemot*.
Now we also have a tradition, or we'll learn it out, we'll
see from the פסוקים *pesukim*, that when you do choose to cut
your hair, you actually then have to bring three קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*.
Okay, so we learn it out from אבשלום *Avshalom*. If you look
at תוספות *Tosfos*, the last תוספות *Tosfos* of the דף *daf*. ומביא
ג' בהמות בשעה שמיקל *umevi gimmel behemot beshaa she'meikel*. When you are
sort of cutting your hair. הלכה halakha למשה מסיני *Halacha Lemoshe MiSinai*,
there's a tradition, ואסמכתא מאבשלום *ve'asmachta me'Avshalom*, and we learn it out
from אבשלום *Avshalom* or we support it by the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
of אבשלום *Avshalom* דאמר אשלמה נדרי *de'amar ashalleima nidi*. So I will
fulfill my vow. So what's my vow? Meaning some type of a
קרבן korban, *korban*. So חטאת chattas עולה olah ושלמים כנזיר טהור *chatat
ola veshelamim kenazir tahor*. And it would be the same type of
three animal sacrifices that a נזיר nazir טהור *nazir tahor* would bring
at the completion of his נזירות *nezirut*. So in a way, there's
some type of a virtual completion of the נזירות *nezirut*. You're not
really ending it, it's forever, but by bringing these קרבנות *korbanot*, you
somehow open up an allowance like to allow you to cut your
hair, but obviously then you have to continue being a נזיר nazir,
*nazir*. Okay, that's נזיר nazir. עולם *nazir olam*. You have your hand
up? No. Okay, that would be a נזיר nazir, עולם *nazir olam*,
one minute. Okay, so you have this allowance when you bring these
if you bring these קרבנות *korbanot*. ואם נטמא *ve'im nitma*, but the
laws of טומאה tumah. *tumah* are normal. If you become טמא tamei
*tamei*, מביא קרבן טומאה korban tumah. *meivi korban tumah*. You have to
bring a קרבן korban *korban* of טומאה tumah, *tumah*. There's no difference
in the laws of טומאה tumah, *tumah*. ונזיר שמשון Shimshon *venazir Shimshon*,
נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon. *nazir Shimshon* is the mirror image. הכביד שערו
אינו מיקל *hichbid se'aro eino meikel*. If your hair gets too heavy
you are not allowed to trim it or do anything to lighten
its weight. Okay, there's no allowance when it comes to hair, right?
I think we know that about שמשון Shimshon *Shimshon*, right? Scissors and
hair didn't go too well together for him. Okay, so there is
no allowance there. ואם נטמא *ve'im nitma*, but if you become טמא
tamei *tamei*, אינו *eino* You don't have to bring a קרבן. korban.
There is more allowance when it comes to טומאה. tumah. What the
גמרא Gemara is going to look at is it sounds like you
still have violated, you're still prohibited to become טמא, tamei, but you
don't have to bring a קרבן. korban. שמשון Shimshon's did not seem
to have any compunctions about becoming טמא, tamei so we'll get to
that in the גמרא. Gemara But basically, they're mirror images. The נזיר
nazir? עולם has no allowance by טומאה, tumah, has an allowance for
hair. שמשון Shimshon. has no allowance for hair and has an allowance
for טומאה, exactly reflecting שמשון's Shimshon, reality. Yes? I had a question.
Is the נזיר nazir? subject to הפרה Hafarah in the same way
as other נדרים? Nedarim?
Oh, הפרה, Hafarah, yes, so the same way as התרה, Hatara, so
we just asked as התרה Hatara and we did, and yes, הפרה
Hafarah as well, and that came up I believe there were some
examples of that in the last פרק, perek, so, I mean in
the last פרק perek of נדרים. Nedarim.
So the definition of a נזיר עולם is that it's a נזירות
with the allowance for cutting of the hair? So it's still a
thirty-day...
No, the עולם means—the עולם means
you
only get the allowance because you basically have bought into a permanent
נזירות. Okay, you cannot end it unless you retroactively undo it. Okay,
so let's see the גמרא. Gemara נזיר עולם מאן דכר שמיה? Nazir
Olam man d'char shemei? First of all, how can you say what's
the difference between שמשון Shimshon. and נזיר עולם without having introduced the
idea of נזיר עולם? So the גמרא Gemara says: Fine, מחסרא מחסרא
והכי קתני, michsarei michsara vehachi tani, we'll squeeze that in. האומר הריני
נזיר עולם הרי זה נזיר עולם. ha'omer hareni Nazir Olam harei zeh
Nazir Olam. Okay, by the way, there's also this idea called a
נזיר עולם. Good. Now that we've said that, מה בין נזיר עולם
לנזיר שמשון? Shimshon What is the difference? נזיר עולם הכביד שערו מקילי
בתער ומביא שלש בהמות. Nazir Olam hichbid se'aro meikeil betaar umeivi shalosh
behemot. A נזיר עולם has an allowance by hair, if it gets
too heavy you can cut it, you have to bring קרבנות. ואם
נטמא מביא קרבן טומאה, ve'im nitma meivi korban tumah,
but no allowance by טומאה. נזיר שמשון הכביד שערו אינו מקילי בתער.
Nazir Shimshon hichbid se'aro eino meikeil betaar. נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon, there
is no allowance by the hair, you cannot lighten the hair. ואינו
מביא קרבן טומאה, ve'eino meivi korban tumah, but there is an allowance
by the טומאה, you do not have to bring a קרבן. And
now the גמרא Gemara gets to this question because saying you don't
have to bring a קרבן still seems like there's a fundamental problem.
So the גמרא Gemara says: קרבן הוא דלא מייתי אבל נזירות חיילא
עליה? korban hu delo maitei aval nezirut chayla alei? It sounds like
you don't bring a קרבן but נזירות still prohibits you, the nature
of the נזירות is that it prohibits you from becoming טמא. tamei
מני
מתניתין? mani matnitin? Who's our משנה going
like? לא רבי יהודה ולא רבי שמעון. lo Rabbi Yehuda velo Rabbi
Shimon. It's not like either side of the debate that we're aware
of. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא: braita: רבי יהודה אומר
נזיר שמשון מותר לטמא למתים. Rabbi Yehuda omer Nazir Shimshon mutar letamei
lemetim. נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon is לכתחילה lechat'chila allowed to become טמא
tamei. to dead bodies, שכן מצינו בשמשון שנטמא, sheken matzinu beShimshon shenitma,
that's what happened with
שמשון. Shimshon רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says: האומר הריני נזיר שמשון, ha'omer hareni Nazir Shimshon, לא אמר כלום,
lo amar klum, it's completely meaningless, שלא מצינו בשמשון שיצאה נזירות מפיו.
shelo matzinu beShimshon sheyatza nezirut mipi. שמשון Shimshon never accepted נזירות. Who
accepted נזירות? Either the מלאך malach told him, the מלאך malach basically
said your child will be a נזיר from the moment he's born,
but there was no halakhic acceptance of נזירות. שמשון Shimshon didn't accept
it upon himself, his father didn't accept it for him, we're actually
going to learn that a father can turn—make his child into a
נזיר. That's a really effective threat to get your kid to do
something, okay, so anyway.
Alright, but we don't see either of those by שמשון. Now what's
he saying? Is he saying שמשון wasn't a נזיר? There is no
institution? The simple read of this could be saying like, yeah, the
פסוק pasuk calls him a נזיר but he wasn't a halakhic נזיר.
It's a non-literal reading of that פסוק?
pasuk No, no,
it is a literal reading, it's a non-halakhic reading, meaning what it's
saying is the angel was saying he's going to act like a
נזיר but he is not a halakhic נזיר. Right? So we have
to follow either the angel and telling you all these rules and
these are the rules you have to follow because I, the angel,
have said so, okay, but it doesn't mean that halakhically he's a
נזיר. If you were to go to the rabbis they'd tell you
according to הלכה it's מותר. mutar. Okay, you would have just violated
the words of the angel, right? We'd have to figure out what
halakha that is, I don't know, okay, you know, it wasn't even
a prophet, a prophet you have to listen to, I, okay, anyway,
but that would be one way to read it. That he wasn't
a halakhic נזיר, he was practicing נזיר but not a halakhic נזיר.
However, that's not the way the גמרא Gemara, reads it. The גמרא
Gemara actually reads it as the following. שמשון for whatever way of
course was a נזיר, I mean whatever, the מלאך malach gave him
his status, that was his status. That obviously was a real status
and therefore it was halakhic as well. But when I want to
try to adopt that status, I can't, because the idea here is
the following. How do I become a נזיר שמשון? nazir Shimshon So
we have been thinking until now that it's this institution out there
called נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon and I say I accept upon myself
to be a נזיר שמשון. nazir Shimshon Okay? So that's how we
think about it. But what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying is
that's not the case, because all the cases in the משנה where
you're saying I want to be like שמשון, which means נזיר שמשון
nazir Shimshon is basically what you're saying is I want to take
that נזירות status that שמשון had and transfer it to me. Okay?
That's what you're saying, not this institution, I'm transferring his נזירות status
to me. And therefore what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying is
that status isn't, cannot be, you cannot piggyback on it. Because only
a status as we're going to see in a minute that was
imparted through a נדר neder, can somebody else then transfer to themselves,
but a status that was never imparted through a נדר, neder. you
cannot transfer through a נדר. neder. So there's two ideas here. Number
one is it was never a status imparted by a נדר. neder
You could it seems to be saying still it was a halachic
status, but point number two is נזירות שמשון you do not become
by just saying I'm a נזיר שמשון. nazir Shimshon נזירות שמשון you
come by transferring שמשון's status to you, and that he says you
can't do because of the nature of this. Let's we'll see that
in a minute. But before we get to that we have to
understand who's our משנה going like? Our משנה says you don't bring
a קרבן טומאה. korban tumah But here רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
there's no you can't become a נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon? so there's
no you know you would have to always bring a קרבן טומאה
whatever there's no institution where you can become where you can be
טמא למתים. tamei l'meisim. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says לכתחילה l'chatchila
you could become טמא למתים. tamei l'meisim. So who our משנה doesn't
adopt either position. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara.
says like this. מני? Mani? Who's our משנה going like? אי רבי
יהודה האמר Ei Rabbi Yehuda ha-amar אפילו לכתחילה. afillu l'chatchila. According to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda לכתחילה l'chatchila you could become טמא tamei if
you're a נזיר שמשון. nazir Shimshon? ומתניתין תני u'matnisin tani אם נטמא,
im nitma, if you became טמא, tamei. so which seems clear that
לכתחילה l'chatchila you cannot. אי רבי שמעון Ei Rabbi Shimon and according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon הא לא חלה עליה נזירות כלל. ha
lo chalah alei neziros klal. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says there's no
you can't become a נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon so our משנה clearly
isn't רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם רבי
יהודה היא. Le'olam Rabbi Yehuda hi. Really it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
ואיידי דקתני גבי נזיר עולם v'aidi d'katni gabei nazir olam אם נטמא,
im nitma, since by נזיר עולם it said if you became טמא
tamei you have to bring a קרבן, תנא נמי גבי נזיר שמשון
tana nami gabei nazir Shimshon אם נטמא. im nitma. By נזיר שמשון
nazir Shimshon, it also said if you became טמא you don't have
to bring a קרבן, but really that's an understatement. The real point
is by נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon you're allowed to become טמא. Okay,
so while the משנה makes it sound like by נזיר שמשון nazir
Shimshon. becoming טמא is not as big of a violation, the גמרא
Gemara clarifies and says that actually the משנה really means that a
נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon is לכתחילה l'chatchila allowed to become טמא. Okay,
so that's now what we have. Institution of נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon.
לכתחילה l'chatchila can become טמא and now we're going to get to
this debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
Let's take a look. Okay. לימא בפלוגתא דהני תנאי קמיפלגי. Leima bi-plugta
d'hani tannai kamifligi. Let's say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon disagree on the following debate of תנאים. tannaim. דתנן Detnan
הרי עלי כבכור. Harei alai k'bechor. Let's say you say this loaf
of bread is like this בכור. bechor. Now going back to נדרים
Nedarim you'll remember that one of the ideas by נדרים Nedarim we
discussed this yesterday is called התפסה. hatfasah. התפסה hatfasah means like we'd
like to be מתפיס matfis to grab, you means by connecting something
to another thing that's already has a status, you transfer the status.
So if I basically have right if this here thing is this
is my קרבן עולה korban olah I sanctified this this cow here,
it's an עולה olah it's walking around, and then I take this
loaf of a bread and I say זה כזה, zeh ka-zeh, this
is like this. So the same way this has a status of
הקדש, hekdesh, okay, and and נדר neder is based on a הקדש
hekdesh type of a model, so it's and it's אסור asur and
so on, I've now transferred the status of this עולה olah? to
this this loaf of bread, okay, and that's called התפסה. hatfasah. What
if this wasn't an עולה? olah What if this was a בכור?
bechor? Now why should a בכור bechor be different? Because a בכור
bechor is a קרבן is קדוש kadosh is forbidden in הנאה hana'ah
but I never sanctified it. It automatically became קדוש מאליו. kadosh me'eilav.
So can I transfer a state that was not a state that
was imparted through words? When I imparted the state through words, it's
all in the world of נדרים Nedarim I can then transfer it
to another object even if somebody else transferred the state. You made
something an עולה I can transfer that status to my loaf of
bread. But if something never was part of that world of being
status imparted by words, maybe it's a status that cannot be that
cannot be transferred. So let's take a look. הרי עלי כבכור Harei
alai k'bechor דתניא detanya רבי יעקב אוסר Rabbi Yaakov oser the object
is forbidden, that works. רבי יוסי מתיר Rabbi Yossi matir רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi permits. מאי לאו Mai lav is it not that רבי
יהודה סבר לה כרבי יעקב? Rabbi Yehuda savar leh k'Rabbi Yaakov? רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who holds you can be a נזיר שמשון holds
like holds like רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov who says that דאמר לא
בעינן דבר הנידר d'amar lo bayinan davar ha-nidur that you can transfer
a status even of something whose status was not imparted through words.
Okay? So the בכור bechor status was not imparted through words. You
know who else's status wasn't imparted through words? שמשון. So they both
שמשון was a נזיר through the מלאך malach a בכור bechor they
were both a נזיר from the act of being born, right? The
בכור bechor of the animals from through birth it's a בכור bechor
and you know the angel says, you know, this will be the
law of הנער היולד, ha-na'ar ha-yulad, you know, and from also being
born that imparted the status, so they both have a status not
through words. So the same way רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says you
can transfer that status by the בכור, bechor, somebody could transfer that
status from שמשון even though שמשון's status came about automatically. ורבי שמעון
סבר לה כרבי יוסי v'Rabbi Shimon savar leh k'Rabbi Yossi and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi דאמר בעינן דבר
הנידר d'amar bayinan davar ha-nidur that no. You need, you cannot transfer
a status unless the original status came through a vow, came through
words. So you can't transfer the status of a בכור, bechor, and
you can't transfer the status of שמשון. That came automatically, did not
come through a vow. Okay, so yes, Tell, you had a question?
But this can get in the issue of what is the power
of a מלאך malach to create reality? Yeah, it could. But the
גמרא is not saying that because the גמרא is taking for granted,
it's also not saying like I said before that he wasn't a
halachic נזיר. They're saying he was a halachic נזיר, that was a
status that was created, but it was created through the מלאך malach
and it was not created through a vow. So שמשון, no question,
he was a נזיר, okay? And maybe he did have an allowance
to become טמא למת, whatever. But the question is I can't borrow
that status according to this approach because it was not a דבר
הנידר, davar hanidar, it was not imparted through a vow. Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this, לא דכולי עלמא בעינן דבר הנידר.
lo dechuli alma bayinan davar hanidar. Everybody would say you need to
start with something that came through a vow, okay? And you can't
transfer if it did not start that way. So then why by
בכור bechor does רבי יעקב Rebbe Yaakov say you can transfer it?
ושאני גבי בכור דכתיב ביה לה'. veshanai gabei bechor dechativ bei laHashem.
It says כי תדור נדר לה', ki tidor neder laHashem, okay, a
נדר neder, to God. So the extra phrase of to God means
לרבות את הבכור, lerabbos es habechor, even things that start off as
God's that did not need to be initially vowed. So somehow the
לה' laHashem of the פסוק pasuk. tells us that a בכור bechor
is something that can be part of that world of transferring through
a נדר, neder. but somehow we only learn out בכור bechor from
there. We don't learn out נזירות, we don't learn out שמשון. Okay,
fundamentally you need a דבר הנידר, davar hanidar, there's a special פסוק
pasuk, that teaches us בכור. bechor. We're going to clarify this in
a minute, that's not super satisfying. רבי יוסי אמר לך, Rebbe Yossi
amar lach, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi would say to you, ההוא לה'
מיבעי ליה לרבות חטאת ואשם. hahu laHashem mibaei lei lerabbos chattas veasham.
No, you can't run to בכור. bechor. You need to first include
that you can transfer the status of a חטאת chattas and an
אשם. asham. You can use them for התפסה. hatfasah. Why would I
think they would be different? Those have total קדושה kedushah that came
through your word. No, because let's take because because חטאת chattas and
אשם, asham, it's true they have קדושה kedushah that came through your
word but you know what they're not? They are not a classic
meaning of the word נדר. neder They are not a votive offering,
they are not a freewill offering. A classic נדר neder. is something
that you offer to God that you were not compelled. A חטאת
chattas and אשם asham you have to bring because you're obligated. Now,
the act of sanctifying the animal is called is from the world
of נדרים, nedarim, is from the world of you know changing status
through a speech act. Yes, but it is not in terms of
the motive of the act, in terms of you know the quality
of the act, it is not a type of a offering to
God, it is not a נדר. neder. So I might think that
that gives it a different status and you can't somehow use it
within this התפסה hatfasah world of נדר. neder So that's what לה'
laHashem comes to include, but you can't jump to the case of
בכור, bechor, which was not a status that was imparted by words
at all. Just one sec, let's just finish the thought. He says,
ומה ראית לרבות חטאת ואשם ולהוציא את הבכור? uma ra'isa lerabbos chattas
veasham ulhotzi es habechor? Why do you include חטאת chattas and אשם
asham but you don't include בכור bechor in what's included in this
התפסה hatfasah world? מרבה אני חטאת ואשם שכן מתפיסן בנדר, marbeh ani
chattas veasham shekein matfisan bineder, because חטאת and אשם, asham, even if
they were not freewill, but their status came, you see that word
התפסה, hatfasah, their status, they were grabbed, their status was imparted through
words. And therefore, if I've got to include anything, I will include
that and then that you can transfer to another object. ומוציא אני
את הבכור שאין מתפיסו בנדר, umotzi ani es habechor sheein matfiso bineder,
but not a בכור bechor because a בכור bechor does not come
through words,
so there's no way to include בכור bechor in the פסוק לה'
laHashem that's completely different. And now we'll get to
the nice clarification: רבי יעקב אמר לך, Rebbe Yaakov amar lach, רבי
יעקב Rebbe Yaakov would say to you, בכור נמי מתפיסו בנדר. bechor
nami matfiso bineder. No, you know what? בכור bechor also has a
status that comes through words. How is that? Through a vow. דתניא
דתנו דבי רבנו אמרו, detanya detanu d'bei rabbenu amru, of the house
of our master, presumably רבי, Rebbe, they said: מנין לנולד לו בכור
בתוך עדרו, minayin lenolad lo bechor besoch edro, how do you know
if somebody has a בכור bechor born in their flock שמצוה עליו
להקדישו, shemitzvah alav lehakdisho, that even though it's automatically קדוש, kadosh, there
is a מצוה mitzvah to sanctify it, שנאמר shene'emar הזכר תקדיש? hazachar
takdish? Right, it says the male says, you know, that the בכור
bechor that's born to you, the male, תקדיש לה' אלהיך. takdish laHashem
elokecha. So you have to sanctify it, even though it's already קדוש,
kadosh, you have to sanctify it as well. So he basically says
look, I agree, you can only do התפסה hatfasah with a דבר
הנידר. davar hanidar. This is why the גמרא says everybody agrees that
you have to do התפסה hatfasah with a דבר הנידר. davar hanidar.
Even the one that says you can do it with a בכור
bechor requires in principle a דבר הנידר, davar hanidar, something that status
came through that. He just says בכור's bechor status does come through
a נדר neder, because what you're supposed to do is add your
own level of קדושה kedushah through your own הקדשה hakdashah and therefore
that does have that status as well. And what would the response
be? The response would be, רבי יוסי אמר לך, Rebbe Yossi amar
lach, נהי דמצוה להקדישו, nehi demitzvah lehakdisho, it might be a מצוה
mitzvah to sanctify it, אי לא מקדיש ליה מי לא קדוש? i-lo
makdish lei mi lo kadosh? But its sanctity exists without you. And
therefore since its sanctity doesn't need you the way to explained, even
if you do sanctify it, that was just a מצוה, mitzvah, it
didn't do anything to its status. You didn't do anything. You know,
you said words, it was very nice, you didn't affect the status
and therefore it's not a דבר הנידור. davar hanidur. And רב יעקב
Rav Yaakov would still say no, I could think something could have
קדושה kedusha to begin with and still your words add another level,
change its status and it is a דבר הנידור. davar hanidur. So
רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik has a very beautiful thought about this. He
says, how do we think about the מצוה mitzvah of זכור את
יום השבת לקדשו, zachor et yom hashabbat l'kadesho, making קידוש kiddush on
שבת? Shabbat? Because שבת Shabbat has a sanctity that exists without us.
So he wants to sort of say by modeling, modeling after what
רב יעקב Rav Yaakov says, it might have total קדושה kedusha without
us, but do you just think like רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, מצוה
mitzvah to make קידוש, kiddush, but it doesn't really add anything? We're
just acknowledging it for ourselves. We're not really changing anything about the
קדושה kedusha of שבת, Shabbat, right? It's a way for us to
just acknowledge it. Or do you say like רב יעקב, Rav Yaakov,
no, your act also adds a human level of קדושה kedusha to
something that already had קדושה kedusha to begin with? So it's a
very nice idea that he wants to, that he develops, that the
idea of קידוש kiddush on שבת Shabbat could sort of be actually
adding a level of קדושה kedusha to the שבת. Shabbat. See what
we have here is that everybody says that it is a דבר
הנידור davar hanidur and the only, that you need a דבר הנידור,
davar hanidur, and the question is is that whether a בכור bechor
is considered to be such a דבר הנידור? davar hanidur? Now, חוה
Chava had her hand up way before. חוה? Chava? I was thinking
it would be close, you could read the last bit as the
difference between an אשם asham and a בכור bechor is in terms
of מזיד meizid as opposed to like, you don't really have a
choice with an אשם. asham. Oh, you mean it's a חיוב. chiyuv.
But you don't have a choice with a בכור bechor either. You
have to bring a בכור. bechor. No, do you not have a
choice with a בכור? bechor? No, you can't not do it. No,
no, no, you could not do a lot of things. No, you're
talking about by the פטר חמור, peter chamor, there you can choose
to break its neck. But if you have a בכור bechor of
a sheep or a cow, you have to bring it as a
קרבן. Okay, okay. Yeah. So פשט for רב יעקב, Rav Yaakov, the
only thing in the world, the only item in the world that
would not be a דבר הנידור davar hanidur would be a כהן?
kohen? No, well you could also have interesting words about what you
say about a ולד קדשים, vlad kodashim, about an animal that's born
to a קרבן. Okay, so but is that a דבר הנידור? davar
hanidur? Because it original נדר, kind of like a כהן? kohen? ולד!
vlad! There you go! Maybe! And right, right, there you go. How
about the fact that כהנים kohanim themselves, originally, they also went through
a whole little process? Oh, now that's interesting. Okay. All right, we're
getting into a פלפול, pilpul, but that was fascinating. Anyway, so here's
the question though. If everybody agrees you need a דבר הנידור, davar
hanidur, what the גמרא never gets back to is, so why does
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda say that you can become a נזיר שמשון?
You need a דבר הנידור. davar hanidur. שמשון did not accept the
vow. How'd he become a נזיר שמשון? So the רא"ש Rosh gives
three possible answers. My answer would have been maybe he rejects the
whole idea that it's coming through התפסה. hatfasa. Maybe he says what
I think we would have assumed, that there's this institution called נזיר
שמשון and you're just saying I'm accepting that institution on me. But
the רא"ש Rosh actually gives some other possibilities. Let's take, if you
take a look here at the רא"ש, Rosh, he says like this,
beside here on the right hand column, he says like this. Hands
up who can read that? וכן רב יהודה. v'chen Rav Yehuda. I
have a big גמרא, so it's about, it's like across from the
תוספות ד"ה d.h. דילמא. dilma. Okay, and he says like this, starting
off a line, he says a little bit lower, וכן רב יהודה
נמי מרבי לה' דכתיב גבי נזיר שמשון דדמי לשאר נזירים. v'chen Rav
Yehuda nami marbi l'Hashem dechtiv gabei nazir Shimshon d'dami l'shaar nezirim. Either
it also says by a נזיר לה', nazir l'Hashem, להזיר לה', l'hazir
l'Hashem, so that includes נזיר שמשון, so we get it in through
a back door through an extra word in the פסוק. Number one,
אינמי דרב יהודה סבר דשמשון קיבל עליו נזירות כשהגיע לכלל שנותיו. inami
d'Rav Yehuda savar deShimshon kibel alav nezirut keshehiga lichlal shenotav. Who told
you that he never accepted נזירות? The גמרא said he had to
be a נזיר when he became בר מצווה, Bar Mitzvah, he accepted
נזירות on himself. והכי צוה המלאך. v'hachi tziva hamalach. Of course he
did it, that's what the מלאך malach said. אינמי מנחיל נזירות inami
manchil nezirut or his father made him a נזיר, כדאמרן איש מדיר
את בנו בנזיר. k'damran ish madir et beno b'nazir. Okay, so we'll
say that it was נזירות, that it was through a, through his
own words, through a הפלאה, hafla'ah, it just wasn't in the פסוק,
but of course he of course also was a classic נזיר. So,
fascinating little debate about how did שמשון actually become a נזיר, was
it through an act of, you know, an act of a vow,
an act of an acceptance of נזירות or not? But according to
this, everybody agrees that נזיר שמשון works fundamentally by transferring שמשון's status
onto you, not by accepting this institution called נזיר שמשון. Let's read
a little further in the גמרא. So the רא"ש Rosh imagined שמשון's
בר מצווה? Bar Mitzvah? Exactly. So the גמרא says like this, okay.
So the גמרא says, וגבי נזיר נמי הכתיב לה'. u'gabei nazir nami
hachitiv l'Hashem. I don't get it, if it says by בכור לה'
bechor l'Hashem and we said that we're going to include בכור bechor
by that, although there are some debate if we actually did include
it by לה' l'Hashem or whatever how it works, but let's say
also the what do you do by the לה' l'Hashem that it
says by נזיר? And again, maybe you use that to include נזיר
שמשון but not everybody includes נזיר שמשון. So what do you do
by the לה' l'Hashem that it says by נזיר? ההוא מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא, hahu mibaei lei lich'detanya, like it says. The גמרא *Gemara* tells
us a ברייתא *braita*. ההוא מיבעי ליה כדתניא *Hahu mibaya lei kedatanya*
like we taught in a ברייתא *braita*. אמר שמעון הצדיק *Amar Shimon
HaTzadik* says שמעון הצדיק *Shimon HaTzadik* from time of the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash*, מימי לא אכלתי אשם נזיר טמא *Miyamai lo achalti asham
nazir tamei*. I never ate the אשם *asham* brought by a נזיר
*nazir* who became טמא *tamei*. Other אשמות *ashamos* I’ll eat, even though
they came as a result of sin, unintentional sin, but a נזיר
טמא *nazir tamei* as we said before, being a נזיר *nazir* is
hard enough. You become טמא *tamei*, you have to start the whole
process all over again. And the גמרא *Gemara* has expressed the concern
that a person in that situation might regret ever having become a
נזיר *nazir* and therefore to some degree it makes it like the
whole נזירות *nezirus* was never valid to begin with, like it was
all בטעות *betaut* and so on, not technically you would need to
do a התרה *hatara*, but that makes it as if it was
a חולין בעזרה *chullin ba'azarah* because fundamentally now you probably never wanted
to have been a נזיר *nazir* in the first place. So he
says because of that I was always hesitant or I always refused
to eat the חטאת *chatas* of an אשם טמא *asham tamei* with
the exception of אדם אחד *adam echad*, one man who came to
me from the south, יפה עיניים וטוב רואי *yafeh einayim v'tov roi*,
beautiful eyes, attractive appearance, וקווצותיו סדורות לו תלתלים *ukvutzosav sduros lo taltalim*
and his locks of hair were so flowing and layered. אמרתי לו
בני מה ראית לשחת שיער נאה זה *Amarti lo beni mah raisa
l'shaches sear na'eh zeh*? My son, what motivated you to become a
נזיר *nazir*? You're going to have to now cut off this beautiful
hair. Again, very funny, is a נזיר *nazir*'s hair beautiful or is
he destroying his hair? Right? Because I know we had the language
of נאה *na'eh* before. The simple sense of the פסוק *pasuk* is
that by growing your hair wild, you get yourself excluded from society,
but ironically right, the גמרא *Gemara* before seemed to indicate that maybe
the long hair is something attracting you to be a נזיר *nazir*.
Anyway here you have the person with this gorgeous hair that he's
going to now have to destroy because he's being a נזיר *nazir*
because that's the end of the process. So what made you become
a נזיר *nazir* that now eventually you have to cut off all
your gorgeous hair? אמר לי *Amar li*, he said to me, רועה
הייתי לאבא בעירי *Ro'eh hayisi l'aba b'iri*, I was a shepherd for
my father in my village, והלכתי למלאות מים מן המעיין *v'halachti l'malos
mayim min hama'ayan*, I went to draw water from the well, ונסתכלתי
בבבואה שלי *v'nistakalti babavuah sheli*, and I saw my reflection, ופחז יצרי
עלי *ufachaz yitzri alai*, and my evil inclination sort of was stirred
up within me, וביקש לטורדני מן העולם *uvikesh l'tordani min ha'olam*, and
it wanted to waste me away from this world, it was going
to lead me into a life of hedonism and pleasure seeking. אמרתי
לו *Amarti lo*, I said to my יצר הרע *yeitzer hara*, ריקא
*reika*, empty one, מפני מה אתה מתגאה בעולם שאינו שלך *mipnei mah
ata misga'eh b'olam she'eino shelcha*? Why are you taking pride in a
world that isn't yours in a sort of temporal passing world שסופך
להיות רימה ותולעה *shesofcha lihyos rimah v'tole'ah*? In the end you will
be worms and maggots. העבודה *Ha'avodah*, good מוסר *mussar* for ever and
ever, שאגלחך לשמים *she'egalchecha l'shamayim*. I will shave off this hair for
God's sake and therefore that's why I became a נזיר *nazir* because
I wanted to redirect my life to a life of holiness. This
is like parallel to the myth of Narcissus, right? עמדתי ונשקתיו על
ראשו *Amadti v'neshaktiv al rosho*. I stood up and I kissed him
on his head and אמרתי לו *amarti lo*, כמותך ירבו נזירים בישראל
*kamosecha yirbu nezirim b'Yisrael*. Oh, like you there should be many נזירים
*nezirim* in ישראל *Yisrael*. עליך הכתוב אומר *Alecha hakasuv omer*, by you
for you the verse says, איש כי יפלא לנדור נדר נזיר להזיר
לה' *ish ki yafla lindor neder nazir lehazir Lashem*. This is a
true נזירות *nezirus* that is for God. So the לה' *Lashem* is
telling you not a הלכה *halacha* point, the לה' *Lashem* is telling
you that we have to be very clear that if we're being
a נזיר *nazir* it's truly motivated for the right reasons and not
for the wrong reasons. And this is an ongoing theme right in
the גמרא *Gemara* where the גמרא *Gemara* was very clear in all
מסכת נדרים *Maseches Nedarim* that it did not like נדרים *nedarim*. Okay
that you're a חוטא *chotei* and etc. if you take נדרים *nedarim*.
נזיר *Nazir*, the גמרא *Gemara* has a more ambivalent because you know
a נזיר *nazir* is somebody that tries to be very holy and
it seems to have been a status of religious elevation and at
the same time besides that he's called a חוטא *chotei* when he
becomes טמא *tamei*, there's this question of what's motivating you? Are the
right things motivating you? Is it good to be separate from society,
not good to be separate from society? So there's more of this
ambivalent in the גמרא *Gemara* or these opposing voices. So here the
גמרא *Gemara* is saying is, some people should be נזירים *nezirim*, ירבו
נזירים בישראל *yirbu nezirim b'Yisrael*, there should be a lot like you,
but only if it's for the right reason. It's very, very rare
that people are doing it for the right reason. Okay, we'll end
here next.